Guide to the Lithographs and Charts of George Vancouver's Expeditions 1798
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Lithographs and Charts of Captain George Vancouver's Expeditions
1778
XOE_CPNWS0105bullitt
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA, 98225-9123 360 650 7534 cpnws@wwu.edu
3 linear feet
Thirty-four charts and lithograph illustrations documenting the expeditions of Captain George Vancouver in the Pacific Northwest and South Pacific.
Bullitt, Dorothy Stimson, 1892-1989.
Biographical Note
Captain George Vancouver (1757-1798) was a member of the second British exploratory voyage led by Captain James Cook (1828-1779), and was also aboard the Discovery, which accompanied the Resolution on Cook’s third voyage. In 1791 Vancouver was given command of the ship the Discovery (named in honor of Cook) to chart the Pacific Northwest coast and to help resolve the crisis precipitated by John Meares at Nootka. He remained on the coast or in the Sandwich Islands for three seasons until he sailed back to England 1795.
The collection contains charts and lithographs documenting voyages by British Naval officer George Vancouver in the late eighteenth century.
Collection is open to the public (special handling required and advance notice or appointments requested).
Priscilla Collins and Harriet Bullitt, Dorothy Bullitt’s daughters, donated the collection in 1992.
The Guide to the Dorothy Stimson Bullitt papers can be found at the University of Washington Libraries Special Collections in Seattle.
The charts and lithographs described in this guide were part of a larger selection of rare books collected by Dorothy Stimson Bullitt (1892-1989) and donated to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies by her daughters, Priscilla Collins and Harriet Bullitt, in 1992. Bullitt, founder of the founder of the King Broadcasting Company, is known for her pioneering work in radio and television, as well as involvement in civic matters and the arts. The original donation to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies included a range of bound rare books and accounts of early eighteenth century exploration. The majority of these books have now been transferred to Western Libraries Special Collections and are part of its rare book collection. At least some of the remaining, oversize charts and lithographs are believed once to have been bound together.
Bound journals documenting the expeditions of Captains John Byron, Samuel Wallis, Philip Carteret, James Cook, John Meares, Nathaniel Portlock and George Vancouver (originally donated alongside these charts and lithographs - and from which some of the described materials may have been separated), are now housed and available at Special Collections, Western Libraries Archives & Special Collections, Western Washington University.
Content from this collection has been digitized and can be accessed online as part of Western Libraries' Digital collections. See: https://mabel.wwu.edu/islandora/object/wwu%3A22286.
Bullitt, Dorothy Stimson, 1892-1989--Archives.; Vancouver, George, 1757-1798--Journeys.; Vancouver, George, 1757-1798.
Hawaii--Discovery and exploration--History--Sources.; Hawaii--History--Sources--Maps.; Nootka Sound (B.C.)--History--Sources--Maps.; Nootka Sound (B.C.)--History--Sources.; Northwest Coast of North America--Discovery and exploration--History--Sources.; Northwest Coast of North America--History--Sources--Maps.; Northwest Passage--History--Sources.; Puget Sound (Wash.)--History--Sources--Maps.; Puget Sound (Wash.)--History--Sources.; United States--Discovery and exploration--History--Sources.
Explorers--California--History--Sources.; Explorers--Hawaii--History--Sources.; Explorers--Northwest, Pacific--History--Sources.; Indians of North America--First contact with Europeans--Pacific Coast (U.S.)--History--Sources.; Indians of North America--Pacific Coast (U.S.)--History--Sources.; Voyages around the world--History--Sources.
Expeditions and adventure; Native Americans
- Friendly Cove, Noatka Sound, 1798; Bullitt_1_01; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Humphries, H., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from sketch by H. Humphries.
- Village of the Friendly Indians at the entrance of Bute's Canal, 1798; Bullitt_1_02; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Heddington, T., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by T. Heddington.
- Icy Bay and Mount St. Elias, 1798; Bullitt_1_03; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Heddington, F., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by F. Heddington.
- Port Dick, Near Cooks Inlet, 1798; Bullitt_1_04; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Humphries, H., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by H. Humphries.
- The Crater on the Summit of Mount Worroray-Owhyhee, 1798; Bullitt_1_05; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Heddington, T., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- The Presidio of Monterrey, 1798; Bullitt_1_06; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by J. Sykes.
- The New Eddystone, in Bhem's Canal, 1798; Bullitt_1_07; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, F., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by F. Sykes.
- A Chart Showing Part of the S.W. Coast of New Holland, With the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and the Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_08; Foot, T., Cartographer;; 85 x 67 cm
  Chart shows tracks and various places visited by Vancouver.
- A Chart Showing Part of The Coast of N.W. America, With the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham., 1798; Bullitt_1_09; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 66 x 85 cm
  Chart shows northward track and southbound return leg along the West Coast of the United States.
- A Chart of the Sandwich Islands as Surveyed during the Visit of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham., 1798; Bullitt_1_10; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 85 x 67 cm
  Chart shows tracks of ships and the islands visited.
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discover and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_11; Roberts, E., Cartographer;; 85 x 67 cm
  Chart shows tracks of ships from California to Alaska.
- Views of Part of the South West Coast of New Holland with the Islands of Oparo and the Snares, 1798; Bullitt_1_12; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- Views of Parts of the Coast of North West America, 1798; Bullitt_1_13; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Humphries, H., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by J. Sykes and H. Humphries.
- Views of Headlands and Islands on the Coast of North and South West America, 1798; Bullitt_1_14; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Humphries, H., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithographs produced from sketches by J. Sykes, T. Heddington, and H. Humphries.
- Views of the Sandwich and other Islands, 1798; Bullitt_1_15; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Heddington, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithographs produced from sketches by J. Sykes and J. Heddington.
- Views of Parts of the Coast of North West America, 1798; Bullitt_1_16; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithographs produced from sketches by H. Humphries, T. Heddington, and J. Sykes.
- Views of Parts of the Coast of North West America, 1798; Bullitt_1_17; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Humphries, H., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithographs produced from sketches by T. Heddington, J. Sykes, and H. Humphries.
- Cheslakee's Village in Johnstone's Straits, 1798; Bullitt_1_18; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- A Deserted Indian Village in King George III Sound, New Holland, 1798; Bullitt_1_19; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- The Mission of St. Carlos near Monterrey, 1798; Bullitt_1_20; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- Salmon Cove, Observatory Inlet, 1798; Bullitt_1_21; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Heddington, T., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- A Remarkable Mountain near the River of Monterrey, 1798; Bullitt_1_22; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- The Town of Valparaiso on the Coast of Chili, 1798; Bullitt_1_23; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- The Village of Almandral in The Bay of Valparaiso with a distant view of the Andes, 1798; Bullitt_1_24; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_25; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 86 x 67 cm
  Chart shows details around Alaska coast and tracks of ships.
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discover and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_26; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 67 x 86 cm
  Chart shows details of Island north of Vancouver and tracks of ships.
- Hergest's Islands, Discovered by the Daedalus Store Ship, 1798; Bullitt_1_27; Gooch, M.; 24 x 30 cm
  Chart shows Hergest's Islands.
- Four Remarkable Supported Poles near Port Townsend, Gulf of Georgia, 1798; Bullitt_1_28; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- Mount Rainier From the South part of Admiralty Inlet, 1798; Bullitt_1_29; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Sykes, J., artist; 56 x 43 cm
- The Discovery on the Rocks in Queen Charlotte's Sound, 1798; Bullitt_1_30; Alexander, W., Lithographer; Mudge, Z., artist; 56 x 43 cm
  Lithograph produced from a sketch by Z. Mudge.
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_31; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 66 x 86 cm
  Chart shows details of land north of Vancouver and tracks of ships.
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_32; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 66 x 86 cm
  Chart show details of coast of California and tracks of ships.
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_33; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 66 x 86 cm
  Chart shows details around Kodiak Island, Alaska.
- A Chart Showing Part of the Coast of N.W. America with the Tracks of His Majesty's Sloop Discovery and Armed Tender Chatham, 1798; Bullitt_1_34; Baker, J., Cartographer;; 64 x 86 cm
  Chart shows details of Washington's Coast.